School of Computer Science Institute for Software Research Carnegie Mellon University 5000 Forbes Ave Pittsburgh, PA 15213 Phone: +1 (412) 268-2748 heather.miller@cs.cmu.edu http://heather.miller.am

# HEATHER MILLER

Citizenship

**USA** 

Research Interests Concurrent, distributed, eventually-consistent (edge computing), data-centric, and data-intensive (big data) programming, from the perspective of programming languages. I work on both theoretical ideas & implementations typically in/for the Scala programming language. My goal is to reduce the burden of building distributed systems.

Education

EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

2009 - 2015

Ph.D. in Computer Science Advisor: Martin Odersky

2011 - 2015

University of Miami, Coral Gables, FL

2006 - 2009

2004 - 2006

BSEE in Electrical Engineering, Audio Engineering, with honors, May 2009

Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, New York, NY

**Employment** 

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA

8/2018 -

Assistant Professor

School of Computer Science, Institute for Software Research

Northeastern University, Boston, MA, USA

9/2016 - 7/2018

Assistant Clinical Professor

College of Computer and Information Science

Scala Center, EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

10/2015 - 7/2018

Executive Director, Research Scientist

Founded a new not-for-profit center dedicated to research, open source development, and education surrounding the Scala programming language.

Databricks, Berkeley, CA, USA

8/2014 - 11/2014

Research Intern

Supervisor: Matei Zaharia

Integrated Scala Pickling, our framework for fast, boilerplate-free, extensible serialization focused on distributed programming (OOPSLA'13), into Spark. Developed new function-passing programming model and framework, can be thought of as a generalization of Spark/MapReduce programming model (JFP'18).

Teaching Experience (Classroom) Co-Instructor,

Spring 2019

17-356: Software Engineering for Startups

Carnegie Mellon

Instructor, Designer, CS4240: Large-Scale Parallel Data Processing	Spring 2018 Northeastern
Instructor, Designer,	Fall 2016
CS7680: Programming Models for Distributed Computation	Northeastern
Co-Instructor, Co-Designer, (with Viktor Kunčak & Martin Odersky) CS 206: Parallelism & Concurrency	Spring 2016 EPFL
Co-Instructor, Co-Designer, (with Viktor Kunčak & Martin Odersky) CS 212: Reactive Programming & Parallelism	Spring 2015 EPFL
(Lead) Teaching Assistant, CS 201: Functional Programming	Fall 2011-2014 EPFL
Instructor Designer Rig Data Analysis with Scala and Spark	2017 -

Teaching Experience (MOOCs) Instructor, Designer, Big Data Analysis with Scala and SparkPopular Coursera MOOC on big data analysis using Spark.Course

2017 – Coursera

- Designed lectures and produced lecture videos. Designed exercises and developed cloud-hosted automated graders.
- Between March-November 2017, over 120,000 registered learners.

Lead, Scala Specialization (mini-degree)

2015 -

Responsible for EPFL's offering of a Scala *mini-degree* on Coursera.

Coursera

Assembled offering of 4 Scala MOOCs, topped off with a capstone
project. Taught and produced 1 course in the specialization and
managed the development of the remaining 3 courses and the project.

Lead, Functional Programming Principles in Scala Popular Coursera MOOC on functional programming in Scala. 2012 – 2014 Coursera

- Lead teaching staff member, organized a team of graduate students, managed content production, designed course exercises with cloud-hosted grading, production of lecture videos, etc.
- >400,000 learners across iterations & largest completion rate for a course its size (~19%)

#### Book

## **Distributed Programming**

MIT Press 2018/2019

Heather Miller, Nat Dempkowski, James Larisch, Christopher Meiklejohn, and Philipp Haller

A textbook about the building blocks we use to build distributed systems. These range from the small, RPC, futures, actors, to the large; systems built up of these components like MapReduce and Spark. We explore issues and concerns central to distributed systems like consistency, availability, and fault tolerance, from the lens of the programming models and frameworks that the programmer uses to build these systems.

Source (draft)

A Programming Model and Foundation for Lineage-Based Distributed JFP 2018 **Publications:** Journals Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Normen Müller Journal of Functional Programming Special Issue: Programming Languages for Big Data **Publications:** Simplicitly: Foundations and Applications of Implicit Function Types POPL 2018 Conferences Martin Odersky, Olivier Blanvillain, Fengyun Liu, Aggelos Biboudis Heather Miller, Sandro Stucki ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages Function Passing: A Model for Typed, Distributed Functional SPLASH 2016 **Programming** Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Normen Müller, Joceyln Boullier ACM SIGPLAN International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming & Software Spores: A Type-Based Foundation for Closures in the Age of ECOOP 2014 Concurrency and Distribution Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky European Conference on Object Oriented Programming Functional Programming For All! Scaling a MOOC for Students ICSE 2014 And Professionals Alike Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Lukas Rytz, Martin Odersky ACM SIGSOFT International Conference on Software Engineering Instant Pickles: Generating Object-Oriented Pickler OOPSLA 2013 Combinators for Fast and Extensible Serialization Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Eugene Burmako, Martin Odersky ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Object Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages and Applications Distributed Programming via Safe Closure Passing **Publications:** PLACES 2015 Workshops Philipp Haller, Heather Miller Programming Language Approaches to Communication and Concurrency Centric Systems RAY: Integrating Rx and Async for Direct-Style Reactive Streams REM 2013 Philipp Haller, Heather Miller ACM SPLASH Workshop on Reactivity, Events and Modularity LCPC 2012 FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent **Dataflow Abstraction** 

Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Tobias Schlatter,
Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky
International Workshop on Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing
Invited to Revised Selected Papers on the 25th International Workshop on
Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing, Lecture Notes in Computer
Science, Vol. 7760, 2013

BigLearn 2011

Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky NIPS Workshop on Parallel and Large-Scale Machine Learning Parallelizing Machine Learning - Functionally: A Framework Scala 2011 and Abstractions for Parallel Graph Processing Philipp Haller, Heather Miller Scala Workshop Submitted/In Monotonicity Types Preparation Kevin Clancy, Heather Miller, Christopher Meiklejohn The Essence of Coordination-Free Distributed Computation Christopher Meiklejohn, Kevin Clancy, Heather Miller Selected May 2016 The Function Passing Model: Types, Proofs, and Semantics **Tech Reports** Philipp Haller, Normen Müller, Heather Miller **Specialising Parsers for Queries** April 2016 Manohar Jonnalagedda, Jorge Vicente Cantero, Heather Miller, Martin Odersky Improving Human-Compiler Interaction Through Customizable December 2014 Type Feedback Hubert Plociniczak, Heather Miller, Martin Odersky Self-Assembly: Lightweight Language Extension and Datatype August 2014 Generic Programming, All-in-One! Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Bruno C. d. S. Oliveira Spores, Formally December 2013 Heather Miller, Philipp Haller FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent Dataflow June 2012 **Abstraction – Proofs** Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Philipp Haller External General Chair and/or Program Chair: Service Curry On (Curry On) 2015, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019 Workshop on Principles and Practice of Consistency for Distributed Data (PaPoC) Trends in Functional Programming in Education (TFPIE) 2018 Scala Symposium (Scala) 2013, 2014, 2017 Programming Models & Languages for Distributed Computation (PMLDC) 2016, 2017 Organizing Committee Member: Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages & Applications (OOPSLA) 2018 European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) 2015 - 2019 **Program Committee Member:** Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages & Applications (OOPSLA) 2019 European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) 2019 Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL) 2019

Tools and Frameworks for Big Learning in Scala: Leveraging the

Language for High Productivity and Performance

International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)	2018
Off the Beaten Track (OBT)	2018
Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages & Applications (OOPSLA)	2017
Scala Symposium (Scala)	2016
Symposium on Trends in Functional Programming (TFP)	2016
Software Language Engineering (SLE)	2016
Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC)	2016
Programming Language Evolution (PLE)	2015
Domain-Specific Language Design and Implementation (DSLDI)	2015

#### **External Review Committee Member:**

PLDI 2018, ECOOP 2016, ECOOP 2013, Scala 2013

Artifact Evaluation Committee: POPL 2015

# Diversity & Outreach

## ScalaBridge Organizer

Organizer of free full-day workshops on the weekends aimed at teaching women and underrepresented minorities in computing how to think computationally and how to program in Scala.

ScalaBridge Chapters: Basel (CH), Zürich (CH), Copenhagen (DK), Boston (US).

## **Open Source**

## Scala Programming Language, member of the Scala team

2011 -

- Scala Spores (Scala Improvement Proposal SIP-21), project lead novel type-based abstraction for using closures safely in concurrent and distributed environments
- Scala Pickling, project lead novel framework for fast, boilerplate-free, extensible serialization. Adopted by sbt, the most widely-used build tool for Scala. Popular open-source project on GitHub with >820 stars & dozens of contributors
- Scala Futures & Promises (Scala Improvement Proposal SIP-14), *team member* unified non-blocking concurrency substrate for Scala, Akka, Play, and others
- Scala Documentation, *creator*, *writer*, *lead maintainer* a central website for community-driven documentation for the Scala programming language and core libraries
- Scaladoc, co-maintainer documentation tool for Scala's official API documentation

## Honors

US National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship	2011 - 2014
EPFL Outstanding Teaching Award	2012
EPFL Computer Science Fellowship	2009 - 2010
Most Outstanding Audio Engineering Student, University of Miami	2009
Most Outstanding Eta Kappa Nu Student, University of Miami	2009
Information Technology Scholarship, University of Miami	2006 - 2009
John Farina Family Scholarship, University of Miami	2006 - 2009
Eta Kappa Nu	2008

Tau Beta Pi SMART US Department of Defense Scholarship Alternate	2008 2007
Cooper Union Full Tuition Scholarship	2004 – 2006
Towards Language Support for Distributed Systems London, UK. November 9, 2018	Code Mesh 2018 (invited)
What Happened to Distributed Programming Languages? Boston, MA, USA. November 6, 2018	SPLASH-I 2018 (invited)
Towards Language Support for Distributed Systems St. Louis, MO, USA. September 27, 2018	Strange Loop 2018
I'm a Young Assistant Professor: AMA. + Heather's Unsolicited Advice About Grad School St. Louis, MO, USA. September 23, 2018	PLMW 2018 (invited)
We're Building On Hollowed Foundations: Worrying Trends in Open Source and What You Can Actually Do About It Krakow, Poland. February 22, 2018	Lambda Days 2018 (keynote)
The Dramatic Consequences of the Open Source Revolution: Unrecognized Challenges & Some Modest Attempts at Solutions in Scala Paris, France. April 7, 2017	Devoxx 2017 (invited)
The Dramatic Consequences of the Open Source Revolution & How the Scala Center Hopes to Help London, UK. December 9, 2016	Scala Exchange 2016 (keynote)
Function Passing: A Model for Typed, Distributed Functional Programming Amsterdam, The Netherlands. November 2, 2016	SPLASH 2016
Introducing the Scala Center New York, NY, US. May 10, 2016 & Berlin, Germany. June 16, 2016 (total ~1700 attendees)	Scala Days 2016 (keynote)
Function Passing Style: Typed, Distributed Functional Programming St. Louis, MO, USA. September 19, 2014	Strange Loop 2014
Spores: A Type-Based Foundation for Closures in the Age of Concurrency and Distribution Uppsala, Sweden. August 1, 2014	ECOOP 2014
Functional Programming For All! Scaling a MOOC for Students and Professionals Alike Hyderabad, India. June 4, 2014	ICSE 2014
Academese to English: Scala's Type System, Dependent Types	NEScala 2014

Selected Talks

and What It Means To You

New York, NY, USA. March 1, 2014

Instant Pickles: Generating Object-Oriented Pickler Combinators for Fast and Extensible Serialization OOPSLA 2013

Indianapolis, IN, USA. October 30, 2013

PL Abstractions for Distributed Programming: Pickle Your Spores!

Indiana University (invited)

Bloomington, IN, USA. October 25, 2013

Spores: Distributable Functions in Scala

Strange Loop 2013

St. Louis, MO, USA. September 19, 2013

Open Issues in Dataflow Programming

Montpellier, France. July 1, 2013

LaME 2013 (invited)

Scala as a Research Tool

Montpellier, France. July 1, 2013

ECOOP 2013 Tutorial

On Pickles & Spores: Improving Scala's Support

for Distributed Programming New York, NY, USA. June 12, 2013 ScalaDays 2013

New York, NY, USA. June 12, 2013

Futures & Promises in Scala 2.10 Philadelphia, PA, USA. April 2, 2013 PhillyETE 2013 (invited)

1 macipina, 171, 0011. 11p111 2, 2013

I am also a frequent speaker in industry, at industrial conferences, developer "meet-ups", and everything in between. Some such events include:

Scala Italy (9/2018, Florence, Italy), LxScala (6/2018, Lisbon, Portugal), Open Source Summit (12/2017, Paris, France), Scala World (9/2017, Lake District, UK), LxScala (5/2017, Lisbon, Portugal), Lambda Days (2/2017, Krakow, Poland), PhillyETE (4/2016, Philadelphia, USA), Code Mesh (11/2015, London, UK), Scalar (4/2015, Warsaw, Poland), f(by) (11/2014, Minsk, Belarus), SF Scala (11/2014, SF, USA), Scalapeño (9/2014, Tel Aviv, Israel), SoundCloud TechTalks (7/2014, Berlin, Germany), Scala Days (6/2014, Berlin, Germany), NEScala (3/2014, NYC, USA), amongst others.

External Activities

Scalawags Monthly Podcast, co-host

2014 - 2016

Students Supervised Zeeshan Lakhani, TBD

2018 -

PhD thesis Carnegie Mellon

Christopher Meiklejohn, TBD 2018 – PhD thesis Carnegie Mellon

Kevin Clancy, Eventual Consistency via Types2017 -PhD thesisNortheastern

**Joceyln Boullier**, Evaluating the Efficiacy of the Function Passing Model 2/2016 – 8/2016 M.Sc. thesis EPFL

**Jorge Vicente Cantero**, *Implementing the Function Passing Model* B.Sc. thesis

2/2016 - 6/2016 EPFL

Thaddée Yann Tyl, Learning Scala Style

M.Sc. thesis

2/2013 - 6/2013 EPFL

## References

Martin Odersky, Professor

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne

**2** +41 21 693 68 63

⊠ martin.odersky@epfl.ch

Jan Vitek, Professor Northeastern University

**2** +1-617-749-8148

⊠ j.vitek@northeastern.edu

Philipp Haller, Assistant Professor KTH Royal Institute of Technology

**a** +46 70 738 28 43

⊠ phaller@kth.se

Matthias Felleisen, Trustee Professor

Northeastern University

**a** +1-617-373-2085

⊠ matthias@ccs.neu.edu

Matei Zaharia, Assistant Professor

Stanford University

**2** +1-510-610-0001

⊠ matei@cs.stanford.edu